The power is real. The story is forever. The time is now.
The Prince of Egypt is a adventure, animation,
drama film directed by Steve Hickner.
The strong bond between two brothers is challenged when their chosen
responsibilities set them at odds, with extraordinary consequences.
Moses (voice), played by Val Kilmer.
Rameses (voice), played by Ralph Fiennes.
Tzipporah (voice), played by Michelle Pfeiffer.
Miriam (voice), played by Sandra Bullock.
Aaron (voice), played by Jeff Goldblum.
Jethro (voice), played by Danny Glover.
The Prince of Egypt is a 1998 American animated musical drama film directed by Brenda
Chapman, Steve Hickner, and Simon Wells, and written by Philip LaZebnik.
It is the first traditionally animated film from DreamWorks Animation, and the first to be
animated entirely in-house at DWA Glendale after Amblimation was closed in 1997.
The film is an adaptation of the Book of Exodus and follows the life of Moses from being a prince of Egypt to a
prophet chosen by God to carry out his ultimate destiny of leading the Hebrews out of Egypt.
It features songs written by Stephen Schwartz and
a score composed by Hans Zimmer.
The film stars the voices of Val Kilmer, Ralph Fiennes, Michelle Pfeiffer, Sandra Bullock, Jeff
Goldblum, Danny Glover, Patrick Stewart, Helen Mirren, Steve Martin, and Martin Short.
DreamWorks co-founder and CEO Jeffrey Katzenberg had frequently suggested an animated adaptation of the 1956 film The Ten Commandments while working for
The Walt Disney Company, and he decided to put the idea into production after leaving Disney and co-founding DreamWorks Pictures in 1994.
To make the project, DreamWorks employed artists who had worked for Walt Disney Feature
Animation and Amblimation, totaling a crew of 350 people from 34 countries.
The film has a blend of traditional animation and computer-generated imagery,
created using software from Toon Boom Technologies and Silicon Graphics.
The Prince of Egypt premiered at Royce Hall in Los Angeles on December 16, 1998, and was released in
theaters on December 18, followed by a release on home video on September 14, 1999.
Reviews were generally positive; critics particularly praised
the visuals, songs, score, and voice acting.
The film grossed $218 million worldwide in theaters, which made it the
most successful non-Disney animated feature at the time.
The film's success led to the direct-to-video prequel Joseph: King of Dreams (2000), and
a stage musical adaptation which opened in London's West End in 2020.
The song "When You Believe" became a commercially successful single in a
pop version performed by Whitney Houston and Mariah Carey.
The song won Best Original Song at the 71st Academy Awards, making The Prince of Egypt the first animated film independently outside of Disney and Pixar films, as well
as the first DreamWorks Animation film, to receive Academy Awards, succeeded by Shrek (2001) and Wallace & Gromit: The Curse of the Were-Rabbit (2005).
The film also won the inaugural Critics' Choice Movie Award for Best
Animated Feature, in a tie with Disney and Pixar's A Bug's Life.
In the decades since its release, The Prince of Egypt has been widely acclaimed and regarded as
one of DreamWorks's best films and one of the greatest animated films of all time.
The film explores themes of egypt, moses, kingdom, pyramid, exodus.
The tone is uplifting and emotional.